Find your way home.
Abominable is a family, animation, adventure film directed by Jill Culton.
A group of misfits encounter a young Yeti named Everest, and they set off to reunite
the magical creature with his family on the mountain of his namesake.
Yi (voice), played by Chloe Bennet.
Peng (voice), played by Albert Tsai.
Burnish (voice), played by Eddie Izzard.
Jin (voice), played by Tenzing Norgay Trainor.
Everest (voice), played by Joseph Izzo.
Dr. Zara (voice), played by Sarah Paulson.
Abominable is a 2019 animated adventure film
written and directed by Jill Culton.
The film stars the voices of Chloe Bennet, Albert Tsai, Tenzing Norgay
Trainor, Eddie Izzard, Sarah Paulson, and Tsai Chin.
The film follows a teenage girl named Yi (Bennet) who encounters a young Yeti on the roof of her apartment building in Shanghai, names him Everest and embarks on an epic quest to reunite the magical creature with his family at the
highest point on Earth along with her mischievous friends Jin (Trainor) and Peng (Tsai), but the trio of friends will have to stay one-step ahead of Burnish (Izzard), a wealthy man intent on capturing a Yeti, and zoologist Dr.
Zara (Paulson) to help Everest get home.
The film was announced in 2010 as its original title Everest.
By 2016, Culton passed on the project after being replaced by Wilderman and Tim Johnson, but eventually
rejoined in February 2018, replacing Johnson, who remained with the project as an executive producer.
DreamWorks announced in December 2016 that the film would be released in September 2019,
with Pearl Studio and Zhong Ming You Ying Film co-producing the film.
The cast were announced between March and June 2018.
In May 2018, DreamWorks changed the title to Abominable.
The music in the film was scored by Rupert Gregson-Williams.
Abominable premiered at the Toronto International Film Festival on September 7, 2019, and was released by
Universal Pictures in the United States on September 27 while Pearl Studio distributed the film in China.
The film received generally positive reviews from critics for its animation and
grossed over $188 million worldwide on a production budget of $75 million.
In Southeast Asia, Abominable has garnered controversy for a scene involving a map of the region with the nine-dash
line, a contested demarcation line used by China to lay claim over a portion of the South China Sea.
Due to this, the film has been banned in several countries involved in territorial disputes with
China over the South China Sea—namely, the Philippines, Vietnam, and Malaysia.
A follow-up television series, Abominable and the Invisible City, was released on
streaming service Peacock and Hulu from October 2022 to March 2023.
The film explores themes of villain, yeti, family relationships, reunion, snow.
The tone is lighthearted.